Guide to the Medieval fragments study collection, 11th-16th cent. M0299
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Medieval fragments study collection
11th-16th century
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
M0299
130 item(s)
Scope and Content
Primarily fragments, these specimens were acquired to demonstrate the development of writing in the western world. A variety of scripts are represented, from Carolingian minuscule to the humanistic hands and the "cancelleresca."
Papers and Photographs: Many items in this collection have been studied by Stanford paleography students. Items for which student papers (usually including transcriptions) are available, are marked by an asterisk in this guide. Also note that photographs are available for more than half of the items, which are marked `+' in the guide. They may be borrowed from the library for a five-week loan period. If interested in either papers or photographs, please ask at the front desk.
Items marked oversize are stored in Box no. 5 in numerical order. Item no. 97 is stored separately in the map case.
Provenance
Purchased, 1969 and 1978.
Access Restrictions
None.
- 11th Century
  - Lectionary? Probably North Italy., 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Old Testament, Book of Esther. Early type of Gothic minuscule., Late 11th-early 12th century; 2 *+
  - Passio S. Teclae. Carolingian minuscule., 10th-11th century; 3
  - Homily? Carolingian minuscule with decorative L. Italy, early or mid-11th century; 4 +
  - Breviary. Gregory the Great, XL Homiliarum in Evangelia Libri Duo. Portion of homily XX. Large initial M., 5 *
- 12th Century
  - Sermo Leonis Papae. Minuscule. Italy., 6 *+ (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Homily? Large minuscule. Germany, circa 1200; 7 *+
  - Bible. Characteristic pearl Gothic with decorative initials. England (perhaps Normandy or Northern France), late 12th or early 13th century; 8 +
  - Missal. Lectiones sup. Lib. Sap. et Evang. Matthaei. Gothic minuscule. France, circa 1200, possibly earlier; 9
  - Bede venerabilis, Homilia Evangelii, Bk. 1, homilies 15 and 19. Part of a lectionary. Early Gothic minuscule. Germany, circa 1200; 10 *+
  - Missal? with musical notation. At the bottom, later (square) notes, perhaps a transcription., 11 *
  - Bible. Unidentified passage, perhaps E 2:26., not consecutive. Text in large Gothic minuscule; commentary in smaller professional contemporary hand., 12 +; 2 leaves
  - Breviary. Dominica XXa per Penthecosteum. With neumes. Fine early German large minuscule. Germany., 13 +
  - Corpus Juris Civilis Justiniani I. Digestiva iv/v. Small minuscule. Italy., 14 +*
    General note
    Digestum vetus, end book 4, begin book 5, c. 1150-1190
  - Gregory the Great, Moralia on the Book of Job, Book 2, parts of chs. XLIV, L, LI, LII. Minuscule. Italy, circa 1100, possibly earlier; 15 *+ (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Laudes? Large minuscule. Italy., 16 +* (Oversize oversize)
  - Epistle of St. James. Headings and initials in red. France, 11th-12th century; 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lectionary. Third Sunday after the Octave of Easter. Heading and initial letter in red., 11th-12th century; 18
  - Commentary on the Old Testament. Initial letters in red. Italy?, 19
  - Missal. Bifolium. Headings and initials in red., 20
  - Missal. Bifolium. Headings and initials in red., 21
  - Augustine, City of God, XXII, c. 8, passage on the martyrdom of St. Stephen., 22 *
  - Gregory the Great, Moralia on the Book of Job, Book XVI, 50-56 (Par. 63-69). Late Carolingian minuscule. Some emendations and marginal notes, same century. Probably France, circa 1100; 23 *
  - Gregory the Great, Moralia on the Book of Job. Some emendations and marginal notes, with grotesques. Probably France, circa 1100; 24 *
  - Lectionary. Commentary by St. Augustine., 25
  - Letters of St. Peter., 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Commentary on the New Testament, concerning St. Peter., 27
  - Lectionary. Gospel of St. John. One illumination, headings and initials in red., 28
  - Lectionary. Passages of the Gospel and homily of St. Augustine and St. Ambrose. Bifolium. Illuminated initial on front of first leaf. Fine illumination representing an ornamental bird on verso of second leaf., 29
  - Lectionary. Bottom of folio missing., 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lectionary. Commentary by St. Augustine., 31
  - Commentary on the New Testament. Not well preserved, one column missing., 32
  - Legal treatise concerning illegal detention. Small, clear script, rubrication, headings and initials alternately blue and red., 12th-13th century; 33
    [Probably from Roffrodus, Libellic ivris civilis]
  - Canon Law. Marginal commentary., 12th-13th century; 34
  - Lectionary., 12th-13th century; 35
  - Paul the Deacon, Homilia 46, In assumptione Sanctae Mariae. As ascribed in J. Migne, Patrologia Latina, vol. 95, col. Bifolium. Northern Italy?, 1497-1505; 36 *
- 13th Century
  - Commentaries on Roman law. Bifolium. A beautiful miniature depicting a teacher, three pupils and their mother, on verso of second leaf., 37 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Text of Canon Law dealing with statues in church., 38
  - Breviary. Homily of Pope Gregory. Bifolium. Illumination in green and yellow., 39
  - Fragment from an unidentified history of Venice and the crusades. Bifolium. Italy, late 13th, possibly early 14th century; 40 *
  - Canon Law text, with gloss. Gothic minuscule. France (Paris?), early 13th century; 41 +
  - Bible. Exodus, 33: 10-14 (recto), 33: 16-19 (verso). With Glossa Ordinaria (marginal)., First half of 13th century; 42 *+
  - Portion of a notarial document. On paper of the earliest type manufactured in the West. Italy, 1285; 43 + (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - De angelis. Theological, perhaps scholastic text. Round minuscule. France or Italy., 44
  - Legal treatise, chapter on divorce. Perhaps from a summa de matrimonio. Minuscule. France., 45 *+ (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Thomas Aquinas, In Duodecim Libros Metaphysicorum, Liber V, Lectiones ix-xii. Small, angular and compressed minuscule. Italy, circa 1300; 46 *
  - Unidentified text. Gothic minuscule. Probably Italy., 47 +
  - Canon Law text. Probably France. (Paris?), 48 +
  - Bible. Interpretationes nominum hebraicorum. Text from the dictionary of Hebrew names which was often appended to manuscript bibles of that period. Gothic minuscule characteristic for Bologna. Italy, probably Bologna, late 13th or early 14th century; 49 +
    (See #61 -Consequitive)
  - Legal text. With marginal gloss. Northern Italy., 50
  - Unidentified text. (Tractatus de monachis?) Gothic minuscule. Two bifolia. Germany., 51 +
  - Old Testament, Leviticus. Large minuscule., circa 1300; 52
  - Civil Law text. De exceptione et venditione. Round minuscule. France?, Late 13th or early 14th century; 53 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Treatise on basic grammatical and logical concepts. France?, 54 +
  - Unidentified scholastic text. France., 55 *
  - Philosophical, perhaps scholastic text. France., 56
  - Canon Law text or: On the Vices and Virtues. Bifolium. Gothic minuscule. Italy., 57 +
  - Apparently a medical fragment., 58 +
  - Dated document. Pavia, Content note on verso., 1230; 59 +
- 14th Century
  - Homiliae. Comm. Biblicum? Gothic minuscule. Aragon, Spain, late 13th or early 14th century; 60 *+ (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bible. Interpretationes nominum hebraicorum. Gothic minuscule. Bologna, Italy, 14th, possibly late 13th century; 61
    (Consequitive with #49)
  - Missal. Round minuscules. Italy, late 14th century; 62
  - Missal. Gothic minuscule. Italy?, 63 +
  - Meteorologica? Late Gothic minuscule. Italy, circa 1400; 64 +
  - Corpus Juris Civilis. De mandatis. With gloss. Bologna, Italy, early 14th century; 65
  - Breviary. Bifolium. Gothic minuscule. Italy, circa 1400; 66 +
  - Missal. Large Gothic minuscule. Italy?, 67 +
  - Notarial document, executed by an English notary and dated in the eighteenth year of King Richard II. England, 1394; 68
  - Civil law text, on certain technicalities of testimony. Gothic minuscule. Northern Italy., 69 +
  - Unidentified (scholastic?) text. Probably Italy, late 13th century; 70 + (Oversize oversize)
  - New Testament, I Corinthians 5: 11 - 10: 11. Bifolium. Large formal hand. Italy?, Late 13th or early 14th century; 71 *+ (Oversize oversize)
  - Last will of Guidone de Robertis. Probably still in semi-finished draft form. Bologna, Italy, 1378; 72 + (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notarial document concerning commercial matters. Signed by the notary Paghanellus. Cursive. Bologna, Italy, 1308; 73 +* (Oversize oversize)
  - French legal document. With interlinear transcription by a 19th c. scholar. Batarde cursive, with text on verso. France, 1389; 74 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lectionary. Characteristic insular Gothic minuscule. England, late 14th century; 75 *+ (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Missal. Fine large minuscule. England, circa 1400, perhaps early 15th century; 76 +
  - English legal documents. First leaf: Landgrant by John Parker of Brightwell and his wife Isabella to Richard Gernay of Byshoppestone. Second leaf: John Parker of Brightwell acknowledges obligation to Richard Gernay of twenty pounds. Endorsed. Richard to have lands as in the first leaf if John fails obligation., 1394; 77 +
  - English legal document. Quitclaim by Lady Alice, wife of the late John of Bysshoppestone to Richard Selby. 8 Edward II, Dated Tuesday, 7 Oct, 1314; 78 +
  - English legal document. Land grant of land in Westwycombe, Moustone and Dunystone by Robert Bury de Monstone to his son Alan. 1 Edward III, Dated the after 27 Jun, 1327; 79 +
  - English legal document. Land grant by John Berhy of Monstone to Richard Pymme. 29 Edward III, 1355; 80 + (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Treasury order to pay the Comte de Scraplon 150 francs d'or a l'ecu for the upkeep of his company. France, dated 1356; 81 +
  - Acquittance for a thousand livres tournois for the despense de l'hostel du Roy notre sire. France, dated 1389; 82 +
  - Five line letter of Charles V when duc de Normandie and Dauphin de Viennois. France, 1361; 83 +
  - Receipt signed by Jehan de Mareschal. France, dated 1371; 84 +
  - Missal. Mass for the fifthteenth Sunday after Pentecost. Gothic hand. Neumes. Germany or Switzerland., 85 *+
  - Dominical? I Maccabees, 1-59, probably Italy, 13th or 14th century; 86
  - Lectionary. Lectio III: II Maccabees 3:25 f. Gothic minuscule. Germany?, 13th or 14th century; 87 * (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Seneca, Octavia, 11. 355b-391 (recto), 392-427 (verso) [ed. F. Leo, 1878]. Italy, circa 1370; 88 *+
  - Passage of a speech. (Boethius?) Bifolium, with interlinear notes., 89 *
- 15th Century
  - Cicero, De amicitia, Parts 3 and 9. Bifolium. Humanistic minuscule. Italy (Florence?), circa 1400-1420; 90 *+ (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Epistola della vedova e del figlio. In volgare. Cursive. Italy., 91 +
  - Book of Hours? Gothic minuscule. Flanders., 92 +
  - Letter from citizen of Urbino to a member of the De'Varzi family in Gubbio. Probably of considerable textual interest. Italy, dated 1469; 93 +
  - Missal, with musical notation on verso. Large Gothic minuscule., Early 15th century; 94 +*
  - Will of Charles de Montmorency. Batarde cursive. France, In French., dated 1469; 95 *+ (Oversize oversize)
  - Missal. Bifolium. Large medieval English Gothic minuscule, with ornamental initials. England., 96 + (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Document concerning a monastery. With two wax seals attached. Spanish cursive minuscule. Spain, 1366 Spanish era 1404; 97 (Map-case map case)
  - Italian legal document. Mentions Bastiano, abbot of Camaldoli, also Americus, who was a bishop of Florence Notarial cursive. Florence, Italy, 1411-1434 c 1412-1434; 98 + (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Prayer book. Bifolium, with red and blue initials. Script is `littera bastarda'. Netherlands?, 99 +
  - Sermons. No humanistic characteristics. Northern Italy., 100 *+ (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Johannes de Pibort. (X) End of a book (verso blank). German Gothic cursive minuscule. Textual interest? (Chevalier Fabricius), 101 *+
  - Vocabularius. Gothica textualis. Southern Germany or Austria, 13th or 15th century., 102 +*
  - Decretals. Including rules for clerics' conduct. Bifolium., 103
  - Bifolium. First folio: List of names of Florentine personalities. Second folio: Spechio de Condan[n]ati et Debitori del Co[mun]e della Montagna Fiorentina. Florence, Italy, 1487; 104
- 16th Century
  - French legal document. Notarial batarde cursive, partly traced over. France, dated 1507; 105 *+ (Oversize oversize)
  - Italian poem. Begins Io t'ho portato tanto tempo honore/... Late cursive. Florence?, 106 + (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - French legal document, with endorsement and confirmation by an Italian notary. Late batarde cursive. Paris, 1571; 107 +
  - Italian legal document giving certain powers of attorney to Girolamo Benivieni. Cursive. Pistoia, near Florence, Italy, 1523; 108 + (Oversize oversize)
  - Italian legal document (sale). Instromento di Vendita. Cursive with strong `cancelleresca' elements. Padua, Italy, 1581-82; 109 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Unidentified and newly identified
  - Unidentified fragment., 110 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified fragment., 111 +
  - Priscian, Institutum Grammaticorum, Book VIII, 29-34. [Ed. by Keil, Grammatici Latini, vol. 2, pp. 396-401.], 112 *+
  - Unidentified fragment., 113 + (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified fragment., 114 +
  - Unidentified fragment., 115 *
  - Unidentified fragment., 116 +
  - Unidentified fragment., 117 +
  - Book 12, chs. 11 and 12 of an unidentified text, perhaps an early scholastic work. Containing passages from Gregory the Great, Moralia on the Book of Job, Bk. 32, chs. 19-20. England, late 12th century; 118 *+
  - Origen, Commentary on the Epistle to the Romans, as translated by Rufinus. Commentary on Romans 5:1- 5:5. PG 14.831-1294. England or Northern France, probably mid-late 12th century; 119 *+
  - Unidentified fragment., 120 +
  - Bible. Book of Ecclesiasticus, ch. 27:27-32:17. France, probably second half of 13th century; 121 *+
  - Unidentified fragment., 122 +
  - Unidentified fragment., 123 +
  - Unidentified fragment., 124 +
  - Unidentified fragments., 125-130 (Box 4, Folder 3)